Guide to the Susan Wilbur Jones Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Susan Wilbur Jones papers
1873-1970
WA MSS S-2350
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.88
(5 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, writings, and other papers recording Susan Wilbur Jones' years in Europe, Chicago, and Cambridge, Mass. as a student, editor, author, wife, and mother. In addition to much material on Susan's family life and life as a student, the papers contain references to the Chicago literary world, in which Susan and her husband Llewellyn socialized with Harriet Monroe, Floyd Dell, John Cowper Powys, Edgar Lee Masters, Carl Sandburg, and Mark Turbyfill. The correspondence is arranged into personal correspondence, business correspondence, and personal business correspondence. Principal correspondents include Katherine Lee Bates, and cousins Edward Brigham, E. P. Warren, and Cornelia Warren. Also included is a letter from her mentally ill aunt Susan Rice, and a letter from Gyp Taylor discussing life in Paris in 1932 mentioning Gertrude Stein, Natalie Barney, William Seabrook, and Ford Madox Ford. There are also family letters from Susan's mother and father, mostly dating from 1909 when Susan spent a year in Europe; as well as correspondence to Susan and her mother from Susan's great-aunt, Susan C. Warren, and from Susan's grandmother, Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur. The diaries are dated 1912, 1914-16, 1918-1919, 1921-1924. Writings include "Saint Nicholas Eve" and an incomplete essay entitled "Floyd and Margery Dell Throw a Party!". Other Papers include Isaac Levine's printed poem "The Queen of Elfland's Daughter (A Moon Fantasy)" inscribed to Susan and Llewellyn.
Jones, Susan Wilbur, 1893-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from John Waite Rare Books on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 1999. Two additions purchased from Greg French-Early Photography on the Ramona Lazare Fund, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
SUSAN WILBUR JONES, b. 1893
Susan Wilbur Jones, daughter of George W. Wilbur (1851-1931) and Ellen Rice Wilbur (d. 1932) of Chicago, was born in Oak Park, Illinois on January 6, 1893. She attended the public schools in Oak Park and Wellesley College from 1909 to 1913, where she boarded with Katharine Lee Bates, majored in Greek and English Literature, and was elected Phi Beta Kappa.
Upon graduation, she returned to Chicago and attended the University of Chicago, receiving a Master of Arts in English Literature in 1914. She began her career in literature by reviewing books for Llewellyn Jones, literary editor of the Chicago Evening Post.
In March 1917, Susan Wilbur married Llewellyn Jones. They had three children: Llewellyn, born in 1919; Cornelia, born in 1920; and George, born in 1930. Susan's sons both attended Harvard; her daughter Cornelia was mentally ill and was institutionalized at any early age.
From 1917 to 1922 Susan was assistant editor of Poetry, literary editor of the Continent, and staff editor of Comptons' Pictured Encyclopedia's volume on the ancient Mediterranean world. From 1923 to 1933 she joined her husband at the Chicago Evening Post as associate literary editor of the newly established book supplement. During this time she also served as literary editor for Child Life, and for the Chicagoan.
Susan Wilbur Jones had been a supervisor of the Illinois WPA Writer's Project for three years in 1938 when her husband accepted the editorship of the Christian Register in Boston. She moved her household and returned to school to pursue a masters in Slavic Languages from Radcliffe College. She received her degree in 1944.
Susan wrote several short works, as well as a history entitled Egypt and the Suez Canal (Chicago, 1925). She began a career in translation with the Satyricon of Petronius Arbiter in 1927. A Rockefeller grant obtained upon receiving her degree enabled her to translate Gudzy's History of Early Literature in 1949, which she followed with a translation of Romanov's Russia in Manchuria (Ann Arbor, 1952). She switched to Japanese in the 1950s and translated Ages Ago: Thirty-seven Tales from the Konjaku Monogatari Collection (Cambridge, 1959).
In her later years, Susan kept house in Cambridge for her youngest son George, and dabbled in translating. She died November 25, 1969.
Scope and Contents
The Susan Wilbur Jones Papers consist of correspondence, diaries, writings, and other papers documenting Susan Wilbur Jones' years in Chicago and Cambridge, Mass. as a student, editor, wife, and mother. In addition to much material on Susan's family life and life as a student, the papers contain references to the Chicago literary world, in which Susan and her husband Llewellyn socialized with Harriet Monroe, Floyd Dell, John Cowper Powys, Edgar Lee Master, Carl Sandburg, and Mark Turbyfill.
Series I. Correspondence is arranged into personal correspondence, business correspondence, and personal business correspondence. Principal correspondents include Katherine Lee Bates, and cousins Edward Brigham, E. P. Warren, and Cornelia Warren. Also included is a letter from her mentally ill aunt Susan Rice, and a letter from Gyp Taylor discussing life in Paris in 1932 mentioning Gertrude Stein, Natalie Barney, William Seabrook, and Ford Madox Ford. There are also letters written by Susan's mother and father during her youth. The bulk of parental correspondence in this collection is related to a 1909 trip Susan took to Europe at age sixteen. The letters reference Susan's travels and report on family life in Illinois, often inquiring about missing letters or packages. During this 1909 trip Jones sent her family in Illinois her diaries to keep them informed about her life abroad. There is also a significant collection of correspondence from Susan's great-aunt, Susan C. Warren, primarily to Susan's mother ("Nellie"), though letters to Susan and Susan's grandmother, Susan Caroline Warren Rice, are present. Warren's letters are filled with family news and inquiries, commiseration and sympathetic updates about health matters, and reference to travels abroad in Europe and Egypt. There is also a set of advice-filled letters to Susan and her mother from Susan's paternal grandmother, Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur.
Series II. Diaries consists of eight individual volumes. The diaries document the years 1912, 1914-1916, 1918-1919, 1921-1924.
Series III. Writings include "Saint Nicholas Eve" and an incomplete essay entitled "Floyd and Margery Dell Throw a Party!"
Series IV. Other Papers includes Isaac Levine's printed poem "The Queen of Elfland's Daughter (A Moon Fantasy)" inscribed to Susan and Llewellyn as well as a bound illustrated booklet published by Dorothy M. Prescott in Belmont, Massachusetts, in 1958, which tells the story of the Warren family of Waltham, Massachusetts, and how the Girl Scouts became entrusted with the Warren Mansion House and 76 acres of family land. Several items were originally interlaid in this volume, including a note to Susan Jones from the Cambridge School about George's school supplies.
Chicago (Ill.) -- Intellectual life; Paris (France) -- Intellectual life; Diaries -- United States; Editors; Barney, Natalie Clifford, 1877-1972; Bates, Katharine Lee, 1859-1929; Brigham, Edward H.; Dell, Floyd, 1887-1969; Ford, Ford Madox, 1873-1939; Jones, Llewellyn, 1884-1961; Jones, Susan Wilbur, 1893-; Levine, Isaac Don, 1892-1981; Masters, Edgar Lee, 1868-1950; Monroe, Harriet, 1860-1936; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967; Seabrook, William, 1884-1945; Taylor, Gyp; Turbyfill, Mark, 1896-1990; Warren, Edward Perry, 1860-1928; Warren, Susan C., 1813-1893; Wilbur, Ellen Rice, -1932; Wilbur, George W. (George Willis), 1851-1931; Wilbur, Sarah Ann Cook, 1864-1904; Wilbur family -- Archives; Wellesley College -- Students
- Correspondence, 1873-1970; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  - PERSONAL
    - Bates, Katherine Lee, 1913-25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Brigham, Edward, 1943-61, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Drake, Dorothy L., [1914-17] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rice, Susan W., [1916 Dec 23] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Warren, E. P., 1917-28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Warren, Susan C., 1889-1899, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6a-d)
    - Wilbur, Ellen G. ("Mamma"), 1892-1909 (Box 2a, Folder 6e)
    - Wilbur, George W. ("Papa"), 1896-1909 (Box 2a, Folder 6)
    - Wilbur, Sarah Ann Cook, 1892-1898, n.d. (Box 2a, Folder 6g)
    - Correspondence with others, 1874-[70], n.d. (Box 2a, Folder 6h-10)
    - Invitations and Christmas cards, 1873-46, n.d. (Box 2a, Folder 11)
    - Other personal correspondence, 1928 Feb 27 (Box 2a, Folder 12)
  - PERSONAL BUSINESS
    - Correspondence, 1892-42 (Box 2a, Folder 13)
    - Letter to Susan W. Rice, 1919 Apr 3 (Box 2a, Folder 14)
  - PROFESSIONAL BUSINESS
    - Correspondence, 1919-47, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Letter to Llewellyn Jones, 1955 Jun 15 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - THIRD-PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - TLS from Eugene M. Caffrey to Suburban Family Laundry, 1923 Sep 25 (Box 2, Folder 16a)
      Scope and Contents
      With envelope and bill for repairs
- Diaries, 1912-1924; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Diary, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Diary, 1914-16 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Diary, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Diary, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Diary, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Diary, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Diary, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Diary, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Writings, n.d.; Series III
  - "Floyd and Margery Dell Throw a Party! New Year's Eve in the Literary Capital," incomplete typescript, corrected (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - "Saint Nicholas Eve," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous poetry, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous essay and short story fragments (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Other Papers, 1879-1958; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Levine, Isaac. The Queen of Elfland's Daughter (A Moon Fantasy), 1951 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Inscribed to Llewellyn and Susan Wilbur Jones by Levine
  - Prescott, Dorothy M. "Cornelia Warren and the Story of Cedar Hill", 1958 (Box 4, Folder 29a)
  - Materials removed from Prescott's "Cornelia Warren and the Story...", 1939-40, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 29b)
  - Cancelled check, 1916 Oct 30 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Loan document, incomplete, [1930] (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Harvard College Library card, 1947 Feb 28 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Photograph of two unidentified people, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Photograph of a Model T automobile, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Six negatives of unidentified people and places with printed Paul F. Grupe Pharmacist envelope, Oak Park, Ill. (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Universal Portland Cement Co., Monthly Bulletin, no. 88, 1911 Sep (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Headley, Rev. P. C. Memorial poem for Herbert A. Mason, Santa Barbara, Calif., 1879 Mar 18 (Box 4, Folder 37)